so thinking about anger why is it wrong
why is it man Olsen
what can I just get angry to sort out
hey Cody it has arisen someone's doing
something wrong he's being unfair to me
so me getting angry I'm telling him show
him why is that wrong yeah whatever well
because if I'm practicing for Honda yep
you cannot well anybody it's wrong in
itself even if you don't press any
button if something is wrong in our
wholesome means it contains a
contradiction okay where is a certain
discrepancy there's certain wrong
assumption in the nature of that thing
that's what it's unwholesome that's
that's there that's what's in common to
everything that's unwholesome in this
life - what unwholesome means that there
is a there is a contradiction yeah which
if you were to see that thing will cease
so if you were to see the discrepancy of
anger the contradiction of anger
it would have to cease you'll be free
from anger of course when I say removing
the anger doesn't mean it would
disappear overnight because that
underlying discrepancy is basically
because of your attitude so it's your
view that causes that discrepancy it's
your view that's the result of you being
angry and and prone to anger or subject
to anger which means it will take time
for that to undo that but the more you
start seeing the discrepancy the the
less fuel for it you're providing and
eventually that fuel will have to run
out so what is the latest reference
exactly so the discrepancy you name for
a in anger regardless all you wanna
practice funny bond or not is way that
you cannot be angry have the mind of
anger without implicitly
tacitly assuming that it's caused by the
external factor a thing
mm-hmm but why is there the discrepancy
you might ask as in like what's the
other counterpart that would make that a
discrepancy because seemingly anger is
because you said something to me some
angry with you or something doesn't work
so I get angry with it but see that's
the view that that the anger is in these
external things
well actually anger is in you resisting
the discomfort of those external things
so it's one thing on the bottom and
another thing on the surface on the
surface it's yes you made me angry but
on the bottom it's actually I'm angry my
own feelings so to speak I refuse I
resist my own feelings which is why of
this angle which is why assume it's
rooted in you and it's your fault so you
think that you I think I'm angry because
of you so what if you what you have done
because of what the situation yeah like
thinking why you're angry that's it
let's just take experience of anger so
there is anger present has to be with
something external so on that basic
level whether you think about it or not
and why and so on
that's all secondary on the basic level
that presence of anger is order the
contradiction anger is felt where you
feel but it's actually projected on
these levels perception you saw
unpleasant sight perceived unpleasant
smell taste touch and so on thought but
anger is not in those things anger can
never be perceived in the in in your
senses anger is always on the emotional
level why because that's what it's
rooted it's rooted in you resisting the
discomfort of the unpleasant feeling so
you take that resistance of that
discomfort whatever unpleasant feeling
it is caused by this caused by that you
take that discomfort at face value means
you're angry with world well you're
certainly liable to be angry with world
you might not give in to proliferating
that kind of blame towards the external
circumstances but you will certainly
to it you might keep yourself in check
that doesn't mean you're recruiting the
anger of the resistance towards the
resistance towards the unpleasant that's
the root of every anger if you don't
resist that this come uncomfortable
feeling if you allow it to endure and
don't try to get rid of it it's
impossible for you to be angry but then
you still uncomfortable yes of course it
is true that anger was never discovered
the anger was never in discomfort
discomfort was never the problem the
problem is in you not wanting wanting it
and trying to resist it you see but your
anger is never in the discomfort hmm
bless your attitude towards the
discomfort let discomfort anger is
result of that so removing that wrong
attitude yeah basically not cultivating
the wrong attitude towards the
discomfort of the emotion that you might
be feeling that's that they will result
in you having removing the basis for
getting angry like compared to like
obviously to slightly on simple examples
would speak but say you're really weak
physically really fair really sort of
you can't bear much heat sensitive very
sensitive in every way so even the
slight like change in temperature and
you you know you're just overwhelmed and
then you know what do you get anger
accountable or not you're over round
you're being overwhelmed by the
uncomfortable feelings didn't reason
from these discomfortable perceptions
and and yes person without trained mind
when it is subjected to external
discomfort they become irritable they
recommend they start lashing out and
random things and people just because
you know it's too cold too hot or too
hard or too hungry or not haven't slept
enough that's all it takes to basically
shake up people sort of mental state
that they think they're in control just
expose yourself to bit of elements and
you'll see how quickly you're going to
lose control over your mind states
because you never trained to not lose
control of your mind states so somebody
very sensitive needs very little and and
that's it he's already overwhelmed but
imagine now you go used to the heat and
cold and hunger they're really lucky
doesn't bother you know that discomfort
is not perceived as something you need
to get rid of actually becomes
inconceivable the only reason you want
to get rid of it is when you're weak
that's when you're bothered so why would
you want to get rid of it when you're
nobody when you don't feel heat and cold
on your skin anymore because you
conditioned it so to speak
then you've been and try to get rid of
it not trying to get rid of it mmm you
will not suffer on account of it and you
would certainly not become irritable and
angry because there's nothing to get rid
of and that's like when Buddha said that
those underlying tendencies there's a
key lessons to be to be overcome to be
able to be destroyed by enduring and you
know people I thought okay this is this
little niche it's it's actually most of
it will bow down to that the very first
thing you do is sense restraint pains of
renunciation is respond before that's
what is a level of enduring so it's not
like oh hi do this and then not fix the
problem and I'll go back to everything
else that's like your enduring is
undermined by the wrong view your view
should be I in do whatever arises for as
long as it arises
I don't even hope on the level of the
view that I can go back to it after I
enjoyed it there's not about enduring
just about anything enjoying the weather
and becoming a hard person you know I'm
sensitive you got to know what one
exactly it's not about blind enduring or
divine asceticism but for some people
weather might be exactly that in other
words it's not specifically what you and
you it's more like where your reasons
are rooted
what is the underlying view but that's a
kind of a different topic first you need
to start enduring you're gonna have
wrong views one way or the other so you
need to start in your head again you
don't need to go and live on top of
mountain and freeze to death
just stop practicing sense restraint and
you have more than you can handle
enduring me but that is the in doing
that you are subjected to the senses to
the pull of the senses you're subjected
to that external world but now you're
enduring it you're not cultivating your
attitude towards it and that's how
you'll eventually get to see that it's
all rooted in you simply automatically
blindly ignorantly resisting
uncomfortable feelings and indulging
comfortable feelings and there is no
reason for that by the way
ignorance is gojira's there is no reason
that you give in to lust now knowing
that that's why you give in to lust so
that's I mean anger is bad because anger
is always rooted in that discrepancy
some resist I resist
unpleasant feelings and that's going but
it can never free you from that fact
that you are suffering no anger cannot
free you from being unable to endure no
anger is the result so it's the anger is
obviously you know like a symptom you
know I'll give up you have an underlying
condition that makes your skin age
because of that you scratch your skin
because of that the underlined
conditions friends and gets you in voice
so anger is that scratching your skin
sensuality is that's collection of skin
it's not the problem it's the result of
the problem that it's aggravating the
problem hence you need to stop
scratching first sense restraint needs
to be established now to what extent
you're going to take that sense
restraint well that depends in your
environment and how far you want to go
into practice like if you really want to
practice for freedom from suffering
feeling from sensuality you have to be
celibate that sense restraint needs to
be taken all the way up to celibacy
which is the ultimate sensory
but if you sort of you know that's a bit
too much certainly to begin with you
have to then start with five precepts
and then practice entry stream within
that now just I keep the Five Precepts
and now I can be careless and then every
now and then take a trace it and make
the measure the indicator that you are
doing things rightly you've said this
before the indicator which shows that
you are doing things rightly is can be
the the amount with the amount of chaos
that you can tolerate in a way yes
exactly the amount of elements you can
be subjected to without losing your
composure but if you can see it odd I
can endure all this chaos fully composed
things are going well well you certainly
are going in the right direction see the
main problem why people cannot see the
root of anger root of sensuality is in
you resisting whatever present feeling
its enduring within you when reason they
can't see that is because they
eventually automatically react to it
either with sensuality or anger or
distraction so you need to stop that
automatic habitual reacting out and and
you stop that by enduring non reacting
and then if it's if it doesn't feel like
more many more enduring then you
increase your non reacting then you
tighten your sense of strain then you
take on celibacy you go maybe I can do
it for the rest of my life okay do it is
a lay person for a month see what what
strain your mind is under then and grow
from it
and then you see maybe wasn't actually
as bad as you as you projected it to be
either way it's necessary if you want to
actually arrive anywhere in the Dhamma
like even as I said the many times in
the you know it's understandable the people
you know it's understandable the people
kind of wonder I have like the noble
disciples sort of on a second I mean it
was still with sensuality living in the
label they were after take out the right
view after they got a degree of their
liberation not before or while that's
why even in the suitors when the Buddha
was teaching laypeople and they were
getting the right view he would teach
them as we said before generosity
rebirth the whole thing and then the
peddle of sensuality the drawbacks how
little it's not worth those pleasures
must be renounced the danger in it and
then he would teach them to dump on top
of that and then sure if they got the
liberation then they might feel like
okay you know this is this is more than
enough for me I have duties to attend
and then go back to their life but
that's not to say that they arrived at
that liberation through their lay life
lay life is incompatible with it lay
life of sensuality that is not like not
wearing robes that's not what makes your
laymen it's whether you you pursue
centrality or not that's with us
so the even as I said even with all the
wrong views or uncorrect abused that the
person might have you want to basically
start enduring sense restrained enduring
uncomfortable feelings when they arise
you don't need to seek them out but you
certainly should not run away from them
Ida I all I get is going to be a bit is
it life-threatening No then why are you
afraid of it you don't go far to field
no look there was that the industry
another sort of you said there are
certain things that to be wisely avoided
come on elephant wild dog tiger snake or
whatever else things basically can
result in killing you
yeah you recognize I'm acting out of
fear here but there is a good chance I
might die and I'm still not enlightened
so I better not die so they can practice
their separation later if I come across
the wall elephant I might decide to not
run away or something so it's lucky you
never sacrifice your intellect that's
one of the main thing main characters of
the Dhamma yeah you shouldn't act out of
fear but it doesn't mean you sacrifice
your intellect now and go blindly walk
into fire because you know it will just
never act out of fear no you still keep
your reason okay this is out of fear but
if I avoid this out of fear I might get
to live and then I might get actually to
understand and free myself from fear but
if I don't I'm just avoiding
responsibility for my own actions
projecting this I'd go ideal come and
just walk into certain death
they're saying you can't you don't have
to go anyway no to feel you just need to
distrain your your mind from going
everywhere and that's already gonna
cause you to feel a lot more like one of
the reasons why the quickest way to get
in touch with your feelings even in the
you know new-age spiritual man who is
start practicing sense restraint you'll
feel much more mundane things daily
things you will feel feel them amplified
because now you restrained
to make make things that's how you truly
get in touch with your feelings not by
seeking them further out or mystic
mystifying them even further know by
saying no to yourself it will make you
feel immediately centrist strength
equals getting in touch with your
feelings yeah yeah well since the strain
equals you feeling the touch of your
feelings cuz it's not your choice
whether you wanna get in touch or not
you're subjected to them whether you
ignore them yet it's the same yeah your
feelings don't care no you want to
resist it you want to take it even
that's that's a different the feelings
do not care
yeah so the discomfort that is there
will come them regardless of what you
think about it yeah you if you want to
do not so let's say by just sitting
still not going anywhere five minutes 10
minutes yeah if you never if you never
done there's gonna feel like you're
being overwhelmed it so right day this
discomfort this pleasure it's absolutely
possible to use your reason and to
recognize that oh I can't handle this
right now that is that is a very
recognition ah so I can't just suddenly
endure scorching heat and hunger I will
die the body will shut down but that's
one thing and another thing is to then
develop a view that I don't have to deal
with this pressure in the volume because
I can't that's why I don't have to know
that's an excuse so you recognize that
you were unable not strong enough not
trained enough to endure not having
anything to do and not consuming
distractions and sensuality but that
doesn't mean you dismiss that as a goal
to train yourself so to be able to
endure it and not give in to sensuality
that's obvious a person needs to be
developed in the body and in the mind
and for as long as they're not developed
in those things they will be attracted
to sensuality and pulled in anger as
well so you will by developing yourself
a certain necessary threshold of
strength so to speak of self-control in
that manner then you you will not be
maintaining these discrepant actions of
sensuality you will and distraction and
if you know well we have other talks
people can search on a channel where we
talk about what is meant by this sense
restraint it's not about saying no to
everything because saying no to every
site is impossible so this body's meant
by sense restraint is basically saying
of the things that are rooted in video
version delusion and not saying no the
things that are not rooted into this
delusion which means also you need to
look back behind whatever you want to do
whatever you've been doing whatever you
you you are currently doing and planning
to do we have to look when is your
motivation rooted in why am I saying
this why am i doing this why am i
performing this action planning that
action because a person can do that
questioning well why am i beating this
person up because it's the right thing
to do well but that's not questioning
you far enough it's it feel like that I
think to do how do you know what is
where did you prove that's the right
thing to do right thing means thing from
contradiction it feels good for me right
so my whatever it feels for me I'm happy
at the present being beaten up and
getting is okay be partly comments
coming to you because you choose to be
tomorrow that says vipaka
so if somebody chooses to beat you up
you will be indifferent equally today
you will be actually not indifferent you
can still do joy because you're getting
what's coming to you
but see so that's that's disingenuous
because you know there will not be the
case so can you genuinely be filled with joy
so can you genuinely be filled with joy
if somebody beating and abusing up
completely yeah they don't know so then
the view that although this is joyful
this is the righteous action is a
contradictory view because oh it's
righteous if it's not applied
me it's applied to me then it's not
righteous so that's I mean if you
question things far enough you will
arrive at discrepancy will arrive at the
contradiction and then well basically
you have a choice you are gonna pretend
it's something you haven't seen it no
there is no contradiction or you will
realize okay I need to change my views
you can't arrive at a contradiction not
ignore it and not change your views so
you cannot arrive at the understanding
recognition of anger and then be angry
if you arrive at it you'll either have
to ignore what you arrive at it in order
to maintain anger or if you don't ignore
it anger will dissipate
so getting getting angry to protect the
Dumber that getting angry well again
that's a contradiction Fitness it does
not lead to
Nibbana if you have the intent you can
also get angry in order to protect your
idea of Dhamma if you were to order and
find out what the actual dummy is or
what is the closest to what Dhamma has
been when the Buddha was teaching it you
realize well Dhamma is that which is
free from anger free from sensuality
free from sexual intercourse free from
slander free from lying free from
stealing cheating free from everything
and also so if I do any of these
unwholesome things on a counter to
protect Dhamma
I am contradicting it the time so if it
doesn't I mean the only way you can
maintain a contradiction is to ignore
the fact that not push it far enough to
see whether it's a contradiction or not
acting out of deferment it's not freeing
yourself from the farmers no no that's
the result of you not being free you
cannot decide that if I will just decide
it acting out of defilement maintaining
deferment well for me lead to Nirvana
at the Buddhist Blacula no because
that's adult it could perhaps lead to
whatever skewed idea of nirvana you
developed for yourself but you cannot
lead to that which you gonna send Ibanez
well how do you know what I'm gonna say
well read the sutras so but yes they
were back in the day many people saying
how they Sydney vana
no no this is me but they had their own
abundance yeah they're their own
enlightenment and they were teaching it
and even have followers followers who
are like minded Li ignoring basically
contradictions of their own thinking of
their own intellect of their own
existence
you always want to look for the
universal nature of things of your
actions thoughts and so on intentions
you don't want to just although this
feels right right now but I kind of know
the universally if this is always to be
done it's not actually good then it's
not good means it's a contradiction in
its nature it contains that discrepancy
and damage free from these
contradictions in its nature so you
recognize things as they are
that's what that means by the way
nothing spiritual at all as they are as
they factually are free from any
misperception that you might have placed
there so you want to be finding truth
embedded Universal nature so if you know
if you say anger is bad anger is bad for
everyone always yet not you can't
it you want to arrive at that Universal
understanding which is basically the
principle of any philosophy at least
that's how it starts now they might go
in different directions but it is you
have to arrive at a universal nature of
it which is universally killing is
always bad now if you don't know why
that that is you can just adopt the idea
of the killing is always bad well you
can adopt the idea the killing is always
bad and then arrive at it to yourself
and confirm that killing is always bad
anger is always bad say sensuality is
always bad if something is unwholesome
means in its nature it's not good
doesn't mean that it's not gonna feel
good yeah okay doesn't matter how it's
felt it's nice realism you want to
rather understanding whether it's in its
principle whether this is good to obey
this free from contradiction or not free
from contradiction and same with on
other talks like if you also wide
sensuality then a contradiction because
you're genuinely attracted to the ugly
you have perception of beauty in regard
to the disgusting you're not seeing the
disgusting because you put in your
perception immunity first then
disgusting can come in second yet there
is no beauty without a disgusting but
they can be discussed
Beauty so it's because of your view you
are attracted to that which is genuinely
repulsive if it were not repulsive the
attraction would not be possible so it's
repulsive and since a possible to ignore
the repulsive and that's how become
attractive so if it's not repulsive also
freedom from attraction would not be
possible why are you making effort to
see the beauty yeah you are making up
you are selectively picking only as you
could have said on the signs of beauty
and ignoring the fundamental framework
of those signs as in even more general
signs of those particular signs of
beauty and those general signs are
always early it is always unattractive
so in itself as I said regardless of
what you think what you views a
sensuality are in itself existentially
speaking sensuality is a contradiction
angle is a contradiction distraction is
a contradiction plus the version
delusion the fundamental basically
outpourings of the old ignorance for
which every individual is responsible
destruction is a contradiction because
you you want to distract just shut up
they might put you reading well how can
you distract yourself from something
without that being the reason for your
action which means you're carrying it
with you you're doing it because I want
to get away from this so you're not
getting away from whatever you're trying
to distract yourself from because you're
carrying it as the reason for your
action of going away from it so the only
true way of getting away from what's
unpleasant on that level of your
feelings is to not have thought of it
that's how it will subside but not
overnight which is why people cannot
even if sometimes they don't act out of
it they cannot see the connection
between not acting out of it and things
subsiding because it takes repetition
over a period of time of not acting out
of it and then eventually you get to see
that as the cause for things subsided
that's the the the search panel so it
knows the escape from yeah central yes
so--but that's noisy drivin yeah when
you see the right-right connection of
the right things and that's what I mean
before I was saying you cannot arrive at
the right view of the Dhamma because
there is no Dharma before the right view
you cannot arrive at the Dhamma
accidentally because you can
accidentally do one thing once twice
three times five times but without any
apparent discernible result you won't be
doing that thing unless you accept
basically on faith the external
instruction of the Buddha or somebody of
his disciples that tells you no you
should stick to it and keep doing it so
you have no verifiable think through a
census that proves that sense restraint
will remove this sensuality will make
feelings subside and so on but you do it
out of faith and because you do it
feelings will subside and that's the
similarly the Buddha the man the
carpenter with the X who uses the X to
to chop the wood every day and he can't
come like today and look at the handle
and say Oh
yesterday was this much now it's this
much worn off tomorrow look he just
keeps you doing it and not even think
about it he's using it and using it and
using it practicing practicing
practicing then one day he walks in and
says oh I have to replace this handle I
can't use it anymore it's way too thin
well what used to make me suffer exact
no longer suffer you know mess of this
chaos in the midst of the same thing
same care same same things it used to
make me suffer I don't feel anything now
you got it and that's a true freedom if
you don't feel anything no pressure
there will be no burden to deal with the
pressure so your burden less and three
from needing to do anything because
there's nothing being felt and that's
the true peaceful feeling that's the
true pleasure to managing feelings
depression of fears for diminishing the
pressure of feeling say you can't
diminish the feelings but you can
diminish how much you're moved by those
feelings by increasing your strength
yeah but usually people leave that
unchecked and all the acts are aimed at
dealing with the feeling the movie with
the feeling dampening the feeling
increasing the feeling whatever and
that's already a contradiction at the
same time like anger
sensuality oh you think that you think
the problem is in the feeling no the
problem is in you being weak in regard
to what you feeling good or bad see if
you're a weak when you feel Pleasant you
cannot help but welcome it and attaining
the light in it indulging it and act
towards more of that pleasure when you a
weak when you feel something unpleasant
you cannot help but try to get rid of it
denied he noted and not have it arisen
basically you want to get rid of the
discomfort when you are weak when it's
not a pleasant or unpleasant you cannot
help but ignore it
and want to distract yourself face face
your feelings yeah face feelings pretty
much stop pressure on feelings so see
you said something that's upsetting for
me for example that's not the problem
the fact that you can say it again it's
not a problem
now you could tell you my will maybe you
will say it again now there's a problem
the problem is that discomfort it's not
enduring in my experience is a hold on
account of what you said
I'm implicitly trying to get rid of it
I'm resisting it I do not want it so if
you stop resisting it you remove the
basis for anger and if you repeat that
sufficient amount of time you'll see
through it and then be incapable or
becoming angry and that's why I said
before like like sometimes people are
you just have to accept things that have
a reason for you and that's true
partially because when its sensuality
opposite of anger well you are accepting
that too much so if your rule of thumb
is just letting everything be and accept
everything and be one with everything
your rule of thumb then is to accept
things that are already overly accepted
and anger is under accepted so yes you
need to accept it a bit more what you're
feeling in order to stop being angry but
sensuality is overly accepted so
actually you need to be draw yourself
from that acceptance say no to it in
order basically to see through it and
either way
yeah that's the little way yeah so you
can't just a blanket rule of thumb I
accept everything cuz you know what say
that which is already accepted you not
react censor the Buddha meant within
those verses when they asked him so how
did you cross the shore just by not
pushing forward but not swimming
backward by not standing still no
sensing stories the year then you to
feel so when you feel neither good nor
bad exactly so don't try to get rid of
that feeling by distracting yourself
from it so in overly accepting you don't
know you don't accept in under accepting
you accept in either accepting or except
not not accepting you don't ignore so
you don't fight the waves you don't pull
backwards you don't stand still also
what we do you don't fight the waves you
don't pull back what you don't that's
what you do is that negative action you
abstain from this doing in the on this
occasion and that doing on that occasion
that's it only these three things you
need rest that's the method
it's nothing else yeah so is this really
sensuality then I'll say no she's
rooting in anger then I should say yes
to this feeling not to acting out of
anger I'm talking the level of feelings
oh is this how they feel now neither
neither pleasant or unpleasant okay so
should not I know that I should not
basically become stagnant in it because
I will sing sink so there's the
uncomfortable feeling oh so maybe I'm
under Lee I'm under accepting it so to
speak I'm trying to get rid of it so I
need to accept the uncomfortable feeling
for what it is and then the problem
disappears oh there is a extremely
comfortable feeling and prospect of
increasing it oh I need to say no to
that but if you say no to under accepted
feeling you're just doubling down in
your anger and if you say yes to all
except the feeling of sensuality you're
doubling down
and challenge and how will you know
where it is
look where your motivation is rooted
what are you doing what are you doing
for and what's the present enduring
feeling while you're doing that -
planning to do that I want to go such a
such place why oh because some people
they need to say yeah but why do you
need can you not see them just ask
yourself if you question so far enough
you'll see no I genuinely need to do
this practical purpose or whatever or
it'll be oh no I'm just basically bored
and I'm seeking company and I'm trying
to justify to myself oh so you're acting
out of field and you're trying to cover
it up that is a reason so what am I
feeling what is my attitude to this
feeling and how does that am i acting
out of it yeah oh I'm feeling this
pressure of this boredom you know I
haven't been going out for a while okay
but why is that a problem now you have
to recognize it's a problem because
you're being pressured to act so yes
okay I can't handle it I need to do
something fun but don't ignore the fact
that you acted out of weakness because
by not ignoring the fact that you acted
out of weakness you do not devalue the
goal of not acting out of weakness and
that's how eventually you will become
stronger yeah so you have to be honest
with yourself and accept when you are
weak when you're weak exact that is not
going on and it's not mind it's not good
enough yeah because you okay I just I
can't handle it so I I went out and
distracted myself yep fine that's fine
in that regard but it's not fine if you
use that to not justify that you don't
need to distrain yourself and there is
nothing wrong in going there's nothing
wrong in being out but there is wrong in
going out on account to the pressure of
your feelings so in itself very few
things are wrong but if you look at the
word a motivation behind those things
that are done then everything can be
wrong because everything can be done for
the wrong reason and that's what makes
you wrong so if you act out a weakness
you recognize that and then you will you
still do not neglect
you do not ignore you don't cover up you
don't devalue you the value of your goal
to not act out the weakness which means
we do act out of weakness the
discrepancy will be felt how a guilt
remorse or shame shame exactly and
that's a good type because it's from the
point of view of what I value what is
fitting for my values as the Buddha
would say I acted like this and that's
not fitting mmm so I feel ashame good
allow that shape in your next time
you're about to act against your values
well you'll be more aware of what you're
about to do and the more you are aware
of it the less automatically habitually
you like towards it you know what
sensory strength will be easy you're
always making things clear making other
that's the goal that is the goal the
only thing that can change about the
goal is you you can become even clearer
about it even if you're failing even if
if you know your failure well the
weakness if you ignore your failure
means okay you maybe you're not
neglecting you're not ignoring the goal
but you're ignoring the fact that you're
constantly contradicting it which means
there's no problem but even worse thing
than that is on account of inability
basically to not act out a weakness so
the country of constant failures of
acting out a weakness you then reshape
your goal you say no no no no it's you
don't need to be censor strained no no
celibacy is only optional no no no that
the Buddha taught that back in the day
that was applicable now it's not all of
that say even if it were true it's not
for you because it's rooted in you
simply justifying your weakness only if
you were fully free from your weakness
already a light in mind then you can
revisit what the Buddha said and done
and see if it's applicable or not until
then it will be rooted in your own
weakness because you do not see the only
way you could see sensualities you
become free from it fully understanding
it fully seeing it you know the escape
from it so you're now saying no you
don't need to be restrained or you need
to be restrained or you don't need to do
this it's all just stabbing in the dark
and it has to be looted somewhere so
it's going to be rooted in
which you have which is weakness acting
out of my weakness so you first need to
qualify yourself to revisit whether
there is another alternative to be
taught of the Dhamma can be taught
yeah but you don't need to really look
that far I mean you can revisit if you
want but it's pointless effort because
if you have even a degree of
understanding of the Dhamma you'll
realize that yeah there's a reason the
Buddha was called the foremost in in
formulating the Dhamma even previous
Buddha would not so precise an eloquent
and accurate like he was and now you
think you can do away with those
instructions because why ask yourself
you might make sense no I don't need to
do this okay fine now ask yourself why
do I hold such a view what is dead
rooted in fact that am I free from
sensuality or not
not so good applause will be diluted in
just me trying to justify my weakness
because it's not pleasant to deal with
it yes no you can say no but again they
can be an arbitrary answer for which you
will not have support because if you
question no how do I know no you don't
what do you do know what I do know that
did I do act out of pressure and
weakness potential terrorize that can
restrain myself when I go present itself
what I still feel angry
I still hate that person even if I
restrain my act that's good but I still
a them so you don't have a perspective
then and whether you can do away with
sense restraint or not and to what
extent that's what like the Vinaya sila
precepts the whole thing needs to be
taken on first then later on like when
the minds were pure completely from
greed aversion delusion yes you don't
need to keep all the bishops but they
are certain pieces that you cannot not
keep which is all the priests of the
deal with at dinner based in sensuality
killing or killing exactly so precepts
they were rooted around sensuality anger
carelessness listings concealing truth
it's impossible to break those priests
but there were those precepts in between
they were kind of in response to this
and that and that sometimes people try
to bundle the fundamental precepts like
the eight precepts they try to bundle
with all these other arbitrary precepts
of the kind of social structure at a
time oh don't worry you know that this
don't do that like no there's a earth
and sky but even then if you were to
know to do away with them you can only
do once you free yourself from all these
underlying tendencies they would be
resulting in in wrongdoings but anything
any pieces that has to do with
sensuality here will harm cruelty that's
not optional that needs to be taken
beforehand and then when you get to
understand the truth you become those
pieces so you don't need to keep the
precepts of being celibate as another
hand because that is your mode of being
because sexual intercourse is
inconceivable you cannot keep the
precepts of you don't have to keep the
police department or kill anyone because
it's inconceivable to intentionally kill
anyone or not to lie or not lying
exactly you don't know I need to make
their footing of line no it's
inconceivable for you to lie because you
took on the values the fundamental
values through sense restraint through
faith through precepts but then molded
yourself into them so you took the value
of strength
you took the the value of hardship the
goal of ownership and then you haven't
done everything that was preventing you
from fitting in it and that's it